[music]
Let's get
you.
You can't go for
ischech.
Philippines,
>> [applause]
>> Thank you for the introduction. Thank
you.
Manual life lives and breathes longevity
and specifically longevity preparedness
in every single market that we operate
in. And by the way, we're also almost
140 years old. We turn 140 in 2027.
And despite having this global passion
for longevity and longevity
preparedness,
the challenges and the potential
solutions are very local.
As recently as three days ago, I was
going to talk about what we do in the
longevity space around the world and I
was going to spend a couple minutes on
that, but actually I thought let me get
right to the main point. Let me get
right to the heart of the matter.
All of you here in Japan, you are the
lifespan champions. Those slides just
showed it. Living some of the longest
life expecties
in the world.
If you look to your left, to your right,
you all are going to live to their 90,
95,
100, and even beyond.
Yet in spite of that,
there is deep pessimism
amongst Japanese people about living a
long life.
Why is that?
It's because Japanese people have
underinvested in what I call their
wealth span, which is how long they can
comfortably live their desired lifestyle
based on their current assets and income
levels. And you could imagine that if
your wealth span is shorter than your
lifespan, that's going to create a lot
of anxiety and a lot of concern.
And this is just not me saying this.
Many life, we did an Asia care survey
across all the markets we operate here
in Asia and what we found was quite
interesting and Japan was really quite
different than any of the other markets.
In fact, people in United States and
China, more than 60% of them said they
want to live to age 100 and beyond.
Here in Japan, 30% of people said the
same thing. 30%.
Similarly,
we looked and we asked people, are how
are you feeling about retirement? Eight
out of 10 Japanese people said they were
very anxious about retirement.
that compares to four out of 10 in the
rest of Asia. A huge difference, a very
stark difference. And it was so
interesting to see that information that
we actually did a deep dive and we asked
the people who responded to the survey,
what was on your mind? What were you
feeling? What were you thinking when you
answered the survey?
And they said, well, one person said,
well, my after my kids education costs
keep piling up, I don't have any money
left to invest or save.
Another person said that my savings
haven't grown in a while because of
stagnant wages and inflation.
Now, why is the problem now more acute
and more challenging than it's ever
been?
Well, that last quote provides some
clues, which is inflation.
Inflation
is back in Japan.
There's been decades of deflation, but
inflation is back. And I just moved from
Southeast Asia 6 months ago
to Japan. And I personally have
experienced inflation in my short time
here. I very quickly after moving here,
I found my favorite tonkatu restaurant.
I love tonkatu.
I went one week and I said, you know, I
want to get this tonkatu. They said,
"All right, you have free unlimited rice
refills." I said, "Fantastic. Amazing."
I go back one week later, just one week
later, and they said, "You have to
choose your rice, small, medium, or
large. No more refills.
That's it. You get what you get." I
said, "Oh, what happened?" Now, clearly,
this was a way that they were trying to
control
for inflation. Similarly, I go to Famima
Mayasa. I want a coffee.
Go there every day for 3 weeks.
I go back after 3 weeks. One dayto
increase overnight, right? So inflation
is real.
I'm sure many of you are fond of oni
giri.
It's a great snack. My kids love it. I
like it. It's convenient. It's
nutritious.
You know, right now inflation is the
second highest in Japan of any of the G7
economies.
And if you project that inflation rate
forward, whatever could buy you one oni
giri for a year today, if you wanted to
eat one oni giri every day, you're a
45year-old, you retire when you're 75,
you'll only be able to buy one every
third day
if you keep your money in cash.
And the unfortunate reason why that's
relevant here in Japan is because more
than 50%
of Japanese household assets are in
cash.
They're in cash. Why is this? This is
another area where we wanted to
understand a little bit better. And some
of the feedback we got from talking to
survey respondents were well
investments is for experts. So, I just
keep my money in the bank. Somebody else
said, "You need to have expertise to
invest. Everybody else just loses their
money."
And that shows a little bit of the
psychology in the psyche of Japanese
people. Now, there is reason for
optimism.
The government knows this has been a
challenge and about 10 years ago opened
up the Nissa account and with some
increases in the limits in 2024,
we've seen a surge in new Nissa accounts
and now 27 million people in Japan have
a Nissa account. About one for every
five people here in Japan. So progress
is possible. And by the way, from my
experience, and this is the seventh
country I've lived in, both as a kid and
now as a professional working for
Mayife,
nobody deserves to retire and be
comfortable than Japanese people. You
all work so incredibly hard. And you see
that in many different facets of life. I
go to the barber. I go to get a haircut.
It doesn't take very long, 2 minutes.
But nonetheless, there's two people
there. They're both in their 60s cutting
the hair. Then there's an 80-year-old
woman sweeping the floor, right? Just
incredible. The work ethic that you all
have here in Japan is something I've
been incredibly impressed by. So,
Japanese people deserve to live a
comfortable retirement. Now,
as we go forward, why is the pace of
change? Why has it been so slow? Well,
there's been a barrier of silence.
There's been a lack of financial
literacy,
a fear of the unknown.
It's even been taboo to talk about money
investing.
And that's a challenge
because what we need is that human
connection. talking to somebody, getting
advice.
It sounds so basic. I know a lot of the
presentations we're talking about
artificial intelligence. We're talking
about all sorts of things, but that
human connection is so important. And
that's another area where Japan
contrasted so much to the rest of Asia.
In Japan, only 20% of people said that
they've talked to a financial adviser.
That compares to 50% in the rest of
Asia. a huge difference.
And why is that? Perhaps it's a legacy
of the bubble economy. Perhaps it's
Japanese people don't want to lose their
money because they've been hurt and
burned in the past. But it's unfortunate
because the people who have spoken to a
financial adviser,
more than 40% of them feel prepared
compared to less than 20% who haven't
spoke to an adviser.
So really important that human
connection. And so what do we do going
forward? What do we all do to solve what
really is a slow burning crisis here in
Japan? At Mayife, we're experts in asset
building and retirement planning, but
more so we believe in this concept of
wealth span that it's something you need
to nurture and you need to grow same way
you would water a plant.
And in this day and age of artificial
intelligence technology, now more than
ever, that human connection is so
important. But it doesn't need to be one
or the other. And in fact, we are using
artificial intelligence to provide
personalized talking points for our
financial adviserss based on
understanding the clients, their needs
to be able to approach them and give
them personalized advice. So it's not
one or the other. It's using technology
to augment that human touch. And it's
not just me saying it. We actually have
been ranked number one in artificial
intelligence maturity by Evident, an
independent company from the work that
we've done in establishing that
capability. And it complements what we
have is a three-step blueprint to
helping solve for your wealth span.
Number one is you have to invest. You
have to invest. You have to diversify.
You have to get your money out of cash.
It sounds in some ways obvious, but it's
a simple first step. Second is you have
to prepare for retirement and establish
a steady income stream for
postretirement.
And then finally, third, it's about
having inheritance and legacy planning
so you can pass that on to your next
generation.
Now, we believe in doing more than this
though and being present in the
community. And in the last 10 years,
we've sponsored a high school economic
koshin competition to promote financial
literacy competition in and concepts
within high school students and it's
been a huge success and we will continue
to sponsor that event. Similarly, we
have sponsored the Senden Kaiigi
copyright competition where we asked,
"Please give us ideas on what would
encourage Japanese people to get advice
from a financial planner."
In January, we'll be doing for the very
first time a longevity
symposium focused on Wealthpan, which
I'm really looking forward to and I hope
some of you can attend.
There's a saying in Japanese which
surprised me. I actually had to look it
up to see if this was really true. And
the saying is a long life isn't worth
living. And as I dove into why, it
sounds like the longer you live, the
more likely you are to bring shame to
yourself. And that was the concept.
And at main life we chose to challenge
that convention. You saw earlier that
advertisement that photographer was 89
years old. He is 89 years old. Kazumi
Karagumisan
who's living his best life at 89 years
old or 89 years young. Incredible. Still
out photo doing photography living his
life. and living life to the fullest.
And that's what we believe
we should all do and what all Japanese
people deserve. So I ask that all of you
help us
normalize the conversation
about investing, about preparing for the
future. Talk to your spouses, your kids.
Many of you are leaders in your
community, in your companies. talk to
them about the importance of planning
for their longevity so that we don't
just keep adding years to our life but
that we start adding life to those
years. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
[applause]
Financial
Yeah, thank you for the question and I'm
glad glad you asked it because it allows
me to use some of the speech I had
prepared but that I changed. So
essentially what Mayif is doing is as an
example in the United States we partner
with a company called Grail who runs a
gallery test for our customers. It's a
blood test, non-invasive,
that provides early cancer detection.
And in fact, we have testimonials from
customers where it saved their lives.
And even their general physician, their
doctor was saying, "Don't worry, you
don't have cancer." And through this
blood test, our customer in the United
States kept saying, "But check again. I
want an ultrasound. I believe I have
cancer." Sure enough, he did have a
lymph node in his armpit that was
cancerous. They caught it early and he
was okay. Now, similarly in Singapore,
we have a partnership with a company
called Emily. And what that partnership
does is it does a gut microbiome test,
which sounds very, very complicated. In
fact, it's a poop test. Pardon my
technical language. It's a poop test
that checks if you have the right
balance between healthy and unhealthy
bacteria and then provides personalized
advice
around brain health, nutrition, diet.
We also have longevity symposiums that
we've done in Boston, Singapore, Manila
that we will be bringing to Japan in
January. And then finally, last year, we
just signed a five-year multi-million
dollar partnership with the MIT Age Lab,
who have been experts in longevity for
the last quarter of a century to help
redefine what it means to live a longer
and healthier life and how to be
prepared to live a longer, healthier
life. So we really are passionate around
this all over the world. But what's
unique is in the United States,
everybody's thinking, how can I live
longer and healthier? Whereas that is
not the most acute challenge facing
Japan as you showed in your statistics
at the beginning.
[sighs and gasps]
I don't know.
Well, I guess there's no better time to
start than now. Um, that's the first
thing I would say. Let let the power of
compound interest take over, but really
I I I know it sounds cliche and simple,
but I would ask for professional help. I
think oftent times maybe we feel like we
should know everything or we should be
experts in every facet of our life. But
if we have a health problem, we're very
comfortable to go see a doctor. That's
something that's second nature. We'll go
get expert advice. They'll help diagnose
us. They'll help treat us. But why do we
feel that aversion, particularly in
Japan, around getting financial advice?
And by the way, it doesn't mean just go
up to anybody and start talking to them.
Interview them the same way you would
interview a doctor. Talk to them, see
what their philosophy is, get
comfortable. Don't just talk to one,
talk to a couple. But really, don't
hesitate to go out and get that advice.
And again in Japan, it's unfortunate
that only two out of 10 people are going
getting advice when they haven't had the
financial literacy education from the
beginning like they have maybe in other
places. So in Japan more than anywhere
else, I think that advice is needed. So
my advice is to get started is go ask
for help and don't be ashamed. Be
empowered to go get that help. And think
about it the same way you would think
about getting advice for a medical
condition. Fore
speech.
Yeah, I think one thing that we can all
do is actually encourage having those
conversations. ations at the office. If
financial literacy wasn't part of the
curriculum for many Japanese people
growing up, then why not bring that
curriculum inside the workplace and
educate people on the benefits of
saving, investing, preparing for
retirement, which by the way, I'm
focusing on the financial side of it
because it is the most acute challenge.
There's other elements to living a long
fulfilled life, including your finances.
your health, your home, is it set up for
you to live a long life? Obviously, you
want to avoid stairs as one example,
your care, what are your daily
activities, do you have social
connection, community, how will you
manage those transitions in your life?
So, I think that we should all encourage
a dialogue and provide forums to be able
to talk about this stuff with our
employees at the office. It could be as
simple as lunch and learns. I know that
that's still common here and I think
that's a great format to be able to go
out and talk to people about this and
help normalize the conversation, educate
people.
Yeah, I think that's a great question
and I I alluded to in my presentation
I kind of had a hypothesis of what might
be driving that. Obviously, Japan had a
bubble in the early 90s that I'm sure
has left a profound impact on people's
mindset.
However, I wouldn't let that stop you
from investing. Maybe perhaps the lesson
is around diversification, right, which
I alluded to as well in my presentation
about being in a diverse set of assets
and not overly concentrated. As an
example, I'm Canadian.
I don't exclusively invest in Canada.
Canada and the stock prices in Canada
are dominated by energy. So if energy
does well, Canadian stocks do well and
vice versa, right? So it's about
diversifying. And I would say the same
thing about Japan. Japan has seen some
good investment returns and stock
growth. We heard about the Nikkay's
all-time high. But equally, you don't
want to put all your eggs in that
basket. So be willing to invest, be
diversified,
and then be patient. There are going to
be ups and downs. There always is. But
any empirical evidence has shown that if
you stay invested, you will get rewarded
for taking that extra risk through
superior returns. So, I think it's
really about getting started, asking for
help, and getting your money out of just
cash because cash is a guaranteed loss
of purchasing power. You're guaranteed
that you're going to be able to afford
less in the future compared to what you
can afford now because inflation is
finally present here in Japan.
give us any advice.
Yeah, I I guess my my advice would be
not to not to repeat um too much, but I
think uh maybe repetition is good
because it reinforces the main message,
which is
>> don't be afraid to ask for help.
Honestly, go out, meet some good
financial advisors. There are many
reputable ones here in Japan. Talk to a
couple, right? It doesn't need to be.
You just go with the first one you meet.
Interview them and take that as
seriously as you would if you were
hiring somebody into your company or
you're hiring somebody to take care of
your kids. This is somebody who's going
to help you take care of your money. So
do that. Ask for help. And then what's
really powerful in today's day and age
is you can use technology yourselves to
validate to check to make sure you
continue to think for yourself on some
of the advice that you're getting. So
you're not giving up your financial
freedom and putting it in the hands of
somebody blindly. You're putting it in
the hands of a professional and then
you're ensuring that there's checks and
balances on the advice that they give
you. But really, my most important
advice would be just get started because
every single day that you keep your
money in cash, you are losing money. And
that's more true now than it's ever been
in the last 30 years here in Japan.
>> [applause]